Guide to the Rebecca B. Matlock photographs, 1980s-2015, bulk 1980s-2005 RL.11383
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Photographs, 1980s-2000s; 896 items 27 boxes Approximately 875 prints; one photobook; approximately 20 loose printed items.; The photographic prints come in two sizes: the majority are 11x14 inch prints housed in 16x20 inch window mats; the rest are unmatted smaller prints measuring approximately 
  - Russia and Other Regions, circa 1985-2000; 580 prints
    - Landscapes, Buildings, and other Scenes, 72 prints 3.5 boxes
      This subseries begins with a general grouping chiefly featuring landscapes of Russia, the Urals, Crimea, and Tajikistan, and other places. There are snowy landscapes, images of bridges and houses, and lakes. then is further arranged into other small groups which have self-explanatory titles: Around Moscow; Art After Stalin; Buildings in the USSR; Churches in the USSR; Circus (the smallest with only several prints); and On Space, which depicts the Matlocks' visit to a Russian space complex where the space station Mir was being constructed (the workers in the images are mostly women). Most of the prints in this series are uncaptioned. Includes some title cards and panels, and one event poster for an Art After Stalin exhibit and lecture.
      - Landscapes, 19 prints (Box 14)
      - Around Moscow, 3 prints (Box 14)
      - Art After Stalin, 10 prints (Box 15)
        Images feature artists, museum-goers, artwork in various media, and a children in a classroom holding up their own artwork.
      - Buildings in the USSR, 13 prints (Box 15)
      - Churches in the USSR, 15 prints (Box 16)
      - Circus, 4 prints (Box 16)
      - Concerning Space, 8 prints (Box 17)
        During a tour of the Soviet Union's regions and cities, the Matlocks were given clearance to visit the space complex where the Mir space station was being built. In this unusual look behind the scenes in an otherwise tightly controlled area, one can see women workers, the assembly hangars and other workrooms, and the grounds of the complex, which include outdoor sculpture. The location of this space complex is unknown, but it may be the Khrunichev State Research and Production Space Center, or the S.P. Korolev complex north of Moscow.
    - Republic of Georgia and Tbilisi
      Like the Landscapes series, the large Republic of Georgia series is further divided into smaller groups whose titles from an original exhibit panel: Interactions with Americans During Glasnost; Churches and Countryside; Contemporary Leaders; Desperation During Civil War; Euphoria of the Postwar Period; and Tbilisi and Some of Its Residents. Images range widely, featuring rural landscapes; inhabitants and villages; city scenes from Tbilisi; and many types of buildings and dwellings, including churches and one Jewish synagogue. Images from Tbilisi chiefly focus on architectural details around the city, and marketplace scenes.
      Notable people featured in the Contemporary Leaders group include Eduard and Nanuli Shevardnadze, and several leaders of Parliament, one of whom was an author of the 1995 Georgian Constitution.
      A large group of these photographs relates to the effects of the Georgian civil war from about 1988 to 1993. Images in this series include rural elderly, damage to land and buildings, markets, bread lines, and street vendors, and refugees from Abkhazia and scenes from the South Ossetian conflict (1989-1992).
      - Interactions with Americans During Glasnost, 7 prints (Box 17)
        Includes portraits of individuals as well as groups of men and women, and a phtoograph of a street poster in Georgian advertising an exhibit of Rebecca Matlock's work.
      - Churches and Countryside, 18 prints (Box 17)
      - Churches and Countryside (continued), 8 prints (Box 18)
      - Civil War, 22 prints (Box 18)
      - Contemporary Leaders, 8 prints (Box 19)
      - Euphoria of the Post War Period, 8 prints (Box 19)
      - Tbilisi and Some of its Residents, 18 prints (Box 20)
    - Trans-Caucasus (Ukraine), 6 prints (Box 20)
      Chiefly uncaptioned images of a Russian ship, a ship's crew, and naval officials. There are also some images of outdoor sculptures. Chiefly from the Ukraine, but there may be other locations pictured.
    - Russia and Other Regions: Small prints, 95 prints 1 box (Box 24)
      Includes small prints, chiefly 8x11 inches or slightly larger, from these series: Americans and Russians; Andrei Sakharov; At Spaso House; Central Asia and Buryatia; Chautauqua; Faces of Slavic Countries; and Gorbachev and the American Presidents.
    - Russia and Other Regions: Small prints, 96 prints 1 box (Box 25)
      These small prints, chiefly 8x11 inches or slightly larger, consists of images from these sub-groups from the series Russia and Other Regions: Landscapes and Buildings; Republic of Georgia; and Trans-Caucasus.
    - Additional large prints, 2 prints (Box 26)
      A later addition to the collection, these prints chiefly consist of landscapes, portraits, and official meetings. Locations are unidentified.
  - Sarah Caldwell, circa 2000-2005; 19 prints 1 box
    This collection of photographs is related to an autobiography of Boston-based conductor and opera director Sarah Caldwell. The book, titled Challenges: A memoir of my life in opera, was based on a series of interviews conducted with Caldwell in the early 2000s by Rebecca Matlock, who eventually published the book in 2008 following Caldwell's death in 2006.
    Photographs in this series are uncaptioned, and chiefly show Sarah Caldwell attending events, posing with others, and at home. Some served as illustrations for the book. There are photographs of the interior and exterior of her Massachusetts house, several shots of unidentified buildings and architectural details, probably in Boston.
    - Large prints (Box 21)
  - Special Places - USA and Republic of Georgia, 1990s-circa 2013; 27 prints 1 box
    Forming part of an exhibit by Rebecca Matlock called "Special Places," these images chiefly from unidentified places in the United States focus on botanical settings with specimen trees and flowering plants, lakes, and outdoor sculptures. Includes 17 large prints from the USA series, and ten small prints, three of which are from the Republic of Georgia and seven from the USA series.
    - Large prints (Box 22)
    - Small prints, 10 prints (Box 25)
  - United States, 1990s-2000s; 35 prints
    Taken during family trips through the United States, these images chiefly depict landscapes, botanical settings, and wildlife, and buildings with significant architectural interest. The series is divided into three groups designated by the photographer: Alaska, Buildings, and Hawaii. There are seven small prints (all from the Buildings series), and 28 large prints. As with other series, some of these images formed part of exhibits. Other U.S.-related photographs can also be found in the "Special Places - USA" series, which formed a separate exhibit. There are also some U.S. locations in the series on Sarah Caldwell, most likely in Boston.
    - Alaska, 4 prints (Box 22)
    - Buildings, 16 prints (Box 23)
    - Hawaii, 5 prints (Box 23)
    - Small prints, 7 prints (Box 25)
      Images are from the U.S. Buildings series.
    - Additional large prints: Alaska, Hawaii, 3 prints (Box 26)
      A later addition to the collection, these prints were also taken on touristic trips in the 2000s.
  - Other Places, 2000s; 15 prints
    The large prints come from Antarctica, Alaska, Australia, Bora Bora, Canada, the Galapagos Islands, New Zealand, Samoa, and Tahiti. The smaller prints come from unidentified locations; some may be from Japan.
    - Large prints, 3 prints (Box 23)
    - Small prints: unidentified locations, 5 prints (Box 25)
      These prints were originally from a folder titled "Miscellaneous countries, including Japan."
    - Additional large prints, 2 folders; 8 prints (Box 26)
      A later addition to the collection, the locations of these tourist travel prints include Antartica, Australia, Bora Bora, Canada, Galapagos, New Zealand, and Tahiti.
  - South and Central America, 1990s-2000s; 7 prints 2 folders
    A later addition to the collection, the prints in this series were chiefly taken on touristic trips to various locations in South and Central America sometime after the 1990s. Portraits of individuals predominate, but there are also a few images of fauna (coatimundi) and vegetation. Captions indicate the photographs were taken in Chile, Costa Rica, Guatemala, Honduras, Mexico, and Nicaragua.
    - Large prints: Chile, Costa Rica, 3 prints (Box 26)
    - Large prints: Guatemala, Honduras, Mexico, Nicaragua, 4 prints (Box 26)
- Other Papers, 1981-2010 and undated; approximately 84 items
  This series includes a Russian magazine with an article about Rebecca Matlock's photographic work; there is also a small group of loose caption cards separated from photographic exhibit prints; caption labels on printer sheets; and a few exhibit information sheets.
  - Exhibit-related materials, 1980s-2000s (Box 25)
    Small group of caption cards, title cards, and a few fliers related to exhibits and lectures.
  - Issue of Ogonek magazine with Russian-language article about Rebecca Matlock, 1989 July, no. 27 (Box 26)